Speaker: In an acting career which covered 60 years in theatre, in film, and on TV,
from Shakespeare, to Bond, to Game of Thrones, Diana Rigg was an icon,
not only for her acting talent, but also for her incredible style.
Diana was born in Doncaster, in the north of England,
but she lived for the first eight years of her life in Jodhpur, in India,
where her father, Louis, was a railway engineer.
Diana returned to the UK with her mother, Beryl, in 1945.
She went to boarding school, where she acted in many plays.
Her teachers recognized her talent, and when she finished school,
she studied drama at RADA, the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art.
After RADA, in 1959, she got a job with the Royal Shakespeare Company.
Diana made her debut in 1961, playing important roles
such as Helena in A Midsummer Night’s Dream, and Cordelia in King Lear.
She was part of a group of brilliant young actors, including Judi Dench.
Diana didn’t earn much money in the theatre, so she also worked as a model,
and had some small TV roles.
However, in 1965, she got the role of secret agent Emma Peel
in a very popular TV series called The Avengers.
Overnight she became a star, but she continued to work with the Royal Shakespeare Company.
She filmed The Avengers during the day,
and then played Shakespearean roles in the theatre at night.
At this time, women actors were usually paid less than men,
but in her second season in The Avengers, she fought to
get paid the same as the male star, Patrick Macnee.
Her salary went up from £150 a week to £450,
though she said later that no other women in the profession supported her.
After leaving The Avengers, she had many roles in successful films.
In 1969, she was a Bond girl in the film On Her Majesty’s Secret Service,
and played the only woman James Bond ever married.
Diana won many awards for her acting, both in the US and in the UK,
including an Emmy for her role in Rebecca (in 1997).
In 1994, she was made a Dame Commander of the Order of the British Empire, or DBE.
For many of the younger generation, who did not know her in her early roles,
Diana became a star again in the hit HBO series Game of Thrones when,
from 2013 to 2017, she played Lady Olenna Tyrell, ‘Queen of Thorns’.
Her last role was in 2021, in the horror film
Last Night in Soho, where she played the main villain.
The film was still in production when she died in September 2020,
aged 82, and it is dedicated to her.
Diana Rigg married twice, and had a daughter, Rachael,
with her second husband, Archie Stirling, a theatre producer.
When she discovered that Stirling was having an affair, Diana divorced him
and took all his suits to the nearest charity shop!
Diana Rigg loved life, and lived it to the full.
On her 80th birthday, she had an enormous party where she invented a cocktail
called Dame Diana’s Dynamite, and danced all night.
One of the last things she said to her daughter before she died was,
‘Oh, but I’ve had such a life!’